Women's Monument Project fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Women's Monument Project fonds
1981 - 1999
F-101
Q103490186
1.13 m of textual records and other material
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Fonds includes ca. 200 photographs, 3 moving image documents (5 video cassettes), 2 sound recordings (4 audio cassettes), and 2 artifacts.
Women's Monument Project
The information for the administrative history was provided by the Women's Monument Project Committee.
The Women's Monument Project was founded in 1990 by Christine McDowell, a Capilano College student, in response to the massacre of fourteen women at Montreal's l'Ecole Polytechnique on December 6, 1989. Genevieve Bergeron, Nathalie Croteau, Anne-Marie Edward, Barbara Klucznik, Maryse Leclair, Sonia Pelletier, Annie St-Arneault, Helene Colgan, Barbara Daigneault, Maud Haviernick, Maryse Laganiere, Anne-Marie Lemay, Michele Richard and Annie Turcotte all died at the hands of a man who said he killed them because they were women. A few months after the unveiling of the monument, Marker of Change, by artist Beth Alber in Thornton Park in Vancouver on December 6, 1997, the Project became inactive. The Project's objectives were to focus national attention on the widespread problem of male violence against women; to build a permanent public art memorial to the fourteen women and to all women who have been victims of violence; to create a lasting testament to the value of women, the sanctity of human life and the refusal to be defeated by violence; and, to offer employment opportunities to women in all aspects of the Project from fundraising to design to construction. Through its fundraising and consciousness-raising efforts, the Project made contact with thousands of individual donors from across Canada and around the world, with community groups, unions and associations, schools, corporations, government, private foundations and the media.
A Committee coordinated the Project. The floor of the Orientation Stand at the Monument site states, "A feminist project realized by a small group of women in collaboration with Capilano College, with love for all people." During the Project's eight-year duration, from 3 to 10 women actively served on the Committee at any given time. Committee members included Lisa Brisebois, Kim Bruce, Janine Carscadden, Dawn Dalley, Christine McDowell, Vanessa Pasqualetto, Krista Marshall, Lianne Payne, Lindsay Setzer, and Elinor Warkentin. Other members were Susan Anderson, Gail Attara, Rita Beiks, Jennifer Bradley, Lorna Brown, Margot Butler, Karen Egger, Alexandra Ewashen, Maura Gatensby, Cate Jones, Deborah MacFarlane, Kelly Phillips, Wonda Seaboyer, Elena Shragge and Maria Walther. Many volunteers who did not sit on the Committee also participated in the Project. Carol McCandless and Olga Kempo represented Capilano College.
Usually meeting every two weeks, the Committee was a forum for collective decision-making. In 1992 a paid, part-time staff position was created, and in late 1993 a Coordinator for the national design competition was hired for ten months. There was no core funding; these positions were supported through government grants or fundraising.
Capilano College sponsored the Project by providing its endorsement, infrastructure (such as office space and telephones), charitable tax status, and administrative support.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name chosen by the founder of the Project.
The fonds of the Women's Monument Project consists of records created and received in the course of carrying out the Project. Activities documented include Committee and sub-committee meetings, fundraising events, groundbreaking and unveiling ceremonies, site selection, dedication, language selection, design selection, construction, and gallery exhibits.
Includes proposals, reports, minutes, correspondence, speeches, published materials, press releases, news clippings, design competition guidelines, design submissions, construction contracts, Monument inscriptions, drawings, site maps, photographs and slides, videotapes, a cloth banner, and the original maquette and artwork of the winning design by Beth Alber.
Records were originally used and maintained by the Project as a series of office files. In l998, Project Committee members appraised and reviewed the files. In some cases, they reclassified materials to fit within series that the Committee assigned to their records in preparation for donation to the Archives. There is some overlap between series; researchers should review the entire file list of the fonds to determine the existence of all files on a particular subject. The Archives maintained the series as received from the Project.
McDowell, Christine; Photographic materials; Artefacts; Sound recordings; Textual records; Buildings and structures; Women
The records were donated to the Archives by Capilano College in 1999.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
The Women's Monument Project originally operated out of Committee members' homes. It moved to the Women's Centre office at Capilano College in North Vancouver. From 1994 to late 1997, the College provided the Project with its own office. The records were then stored in Christine McDowell's home and transferred to the Archives in 1999.
Capilano College retains administrative files, including donor and other financial records, for legal purposes. However, researchers can find a budget and financial statement in the Women's Monument Project Fonds in the series, "Background Records." The series "Construction Records" contains a budget for construction. A touring exhibit of a selected group of the designs submitted to the competition for the Monument also remains stored at the college. It is available for exhibition.
Some files contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files is restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Researchers should be aware that certain documents contain redacted elements. Redactions were made by the creator prior to donation to the Archives.
Series descriptions and a file list are available.
- Women's Monument background records, 1981 - 1999; F-101-1; 11 cm of textual records 1 moving image document 1 artifact; Language: the brochures and fact sheets are in French and English.
  published
  Series consists of records which were used to define and develop the Project within its social and artistic contexts. Includes reference materials such as statistics on violence against women; original proposals for the Project; speeches given by Committee members at public functions; biographies of the fourteen women; "What They're Saying," a brochure of quotations from well-known public figures who supported the Project; information on other memorials; a budget and a financial statement. Examples of core published materials, such as brochures and the single rose logo and letterhead, are preserved here as well as a cloth banner. Also includes a VHS copy of the film, Marker of Change, donated by the film's producer.
  Moving images; Artefacts; Textual records
  - Related Memorials, 1981 - 1997; F-101-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Project Proposals, 1990 - 1994; F-101-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
    File consists of multiple drafts of the project proposal, plus an information sheet describing the project.
  - Published Project Materials - French and English, 1990 - 1997; F-101-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - December 6 Ceremonies, 1990 - 1996; F-101-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - Other December 6 Memorials, 1990 - 1996; F-101-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - Original Letterhead, 1990; F-101-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
    Open, no restrictions
    Reviewed for access (Mar 15, 2024) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - Violence Against Women Statistics, 1992 - 1994; F-101-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
    File includes statistics and two reports: Statistics Canada's "Violence Against Women Survey: Survey Highlights 1993"; and "Woman Killing: Intimate Femicide in Ontario, 1974–1990" prepared for the Women We Honour Action Committee (April 1992).
  - Femicide Lists / Mary Billy Interview, 1992 - 1998; F-101-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - Financial Statements, 1992; F-101-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - 14 Women's Biographies, 1993; F-101-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - Speeches, 1990 - 1997; F-101-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - Documentary Marker Of Change, 1998 - 1999; F-101-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
    - Marker of Change: The Story of the Women's Monument, 1998; F-101-1-0-0-12-1 (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-2233)
      Moving images
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-101-item7.
  - Capilano College, [ca 1990] - [ca 1997]; F-101-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
  - Women's Monument Banner, 1993; F-101-1-0-0-14
  - Carol McCandless, 1992 - 1995; F-101-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
- Committee minutes and reports, 1991 - 1997; F-101-2; 13 cm of textual records
  Series consists of minutes relating to the decision-making of the Committee which coordinated the Project. During the busy period of 1997, the Committee did not take minutes at every meeting. Also includes annual reports from 1994–1997.
  - Minutes, 1991 - 1992; F-101-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-1)
    Pending review
  - Minutes, 1993; F-101-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Minutes, 1993; F-101-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Minutes, 1994; F-101-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Minutes, 1994; F-101-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Minutes, 1995; F-101-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Minutes, 1995; F-101-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Minutes, 1996; F-101-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Minutes, 1997; F-101-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
  - Annual Reports, 1994 - 1997; F-101-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 101-2)
- Correspondence, 1990 - 1998; F-101-3; 16 cm of textual records
  Series consists of letters received from the public about the Project and examples of letters sent by the Committee in response. Also includes official support letters from community leaders, correspondence with the fourteen families of the murdered women, and correspondence with translators for the project's inscription.
  Correspondence related to fundraising, construction, design of the monument, and the unveiling ceremony can be found in those record series.
  - Letters sent - general, 1991 - 1993; F-101-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters sent - general, 1994 - 1998; F-101-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters of support to Vancouver Parks Board, [ca 1990] - [ca 1998]; F-101-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters sent - fourteen families, [ca 1990] - [ca 1998]; F-101-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters sent - translations, [ca 1990] - [ca 1998]; F-101-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Official letters of support, [ca 1990] - [ca 1998]; F-101-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters received, 1990 - 1991; F-101-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters received, [ca 1990] - [ca 1998]; F-101-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters received, 1992; F-101-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters received - personal testimonials, 1992 - 1993; F-101-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters received, 1993; F-101-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters received, 1993; F-101-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 101-3)
  - Letters received, 1994; F-101-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Letters received, 1995; F-101-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Letters received, 1996; F-101-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Letters received, 1997 - 1998; F-101-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
- Fundraising records, 1990 - 1997; F-101-4; 13 cm of textual records; Material is in French and English.
  Series consists of records relating to the fundraising activities which financed the Project. Activities documented include Reel Change, a filmathon; See Jane Fly, a poetry "bash;" and Lives We Value, a reception. Includes direct mail request letters, and specific requests made to corporations, foundations, unions, associations, VanCity Credit Union and government. Also includes examples of published materials such as programs and flyers.
  - Fundraising - see Jane Fly and other events, 1992 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
    Textual records; Graphic materials
  - Fundraising Events - Lives We Value, 1993; F-101-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Fundraising Events - Filmathon Subcommittee Minutes, 1995 - 1996; F-101-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Fundraising Events - Filmathon Correspondence, 1995 - 1996; F-101-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Fundraising Events - Mistress of Ceremonies and Speakers' Biographies, 1995; F-101-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Fundraising Events - Filmathon Film Tours, 1995 - 1996; F-101-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Fundraising Events - Filmathon Published Materials, 1996; F-101-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Direct Mail - Request Letters, 1991 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Direct Mail - Thank you Letters, 1994 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 101-4)
  - Funding Requests - Associations and organizations, 1990 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Funding Requests - Government: private and crown, 1992 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Funding Requests - Foundations, 1992 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Funding Requests - VanCity Credit Union, 1992 - 1994; F-101-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Funding Requests - Unions, 1993 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Funding Requests - Private and Crown corporations, 1994 - 1997; F-101-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
- Media relations clippings and releases, 1990 - 1998; F-101-5; 8 cm of textual records; Material is in French and English.
  Series consists of material created by the Project for the media, as well as examples of Canadian print media coverage of the Project. Extensive news clippings from 1991-1998 indicate the scope of the public debate which was inspired by the Project and the social issues it represented. Includes press releases issued by the Committee from 1991-1997, and the text of a television commercial created for the Women's Television Network.
  - Press Clippings, 1990 - 1991; F-101-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings, 1992; F-101-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings, 1993; F-101-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings, 1994; F-101-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings - French and English, 1995; F-101-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings - French and English, 1996; F-101-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings - French and English, 1997; F-101-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings - French and English, 1998; F-101-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Clippings - French and English, [ca 1990] - [ca 1998]; F-101-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Press Releases - French and English, 1991 - 1997; F-101-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
  - Television Commercial - Women's TV Network, 1997; F-101-5-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 101-5)
- Monument design records, 1988 - 1998; F-101-6; 21 cm of textual records 2 sound recordings 1 moving image document 1 artifact; Language: records are in French and English.
  Series consists of records relating to the site for the Monument, and its artistic design. Activities documented are site selection, the national design competition (stages one and two), and selection of the dedication languages inscribed on the Monument. Includes correspondence, notes, a site map, subcommittee minutes, competition guidelines, records pertaining to the jurisdiction of the Vancouver Parks Board and the Vancouver Public Art Committee, copies of all 98 design submissions, and questionnaires given out to the public with regard to the dedication languages. Also includes transcripts and audiotapes containing discussions about the selection of seven dedication languages for the site. Also includes the original maquette and artwork for the winning design by Beth Alber.
  Sound recordings; Moving images; Textual records; Artefacts
  Access to some files is restricted because of an agreement with the donor. Please see the archivist for further details.
  - Site selection, 1988 - 1994; F-101-6-1; 4 cm of textual records
    - Background Research, 1988 - 1993; F-101-6-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Correspondence, 1992 - 1994; F-101-6-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Vancouver Park Board Submission and Approval, 1993; F-101-6-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Site Map, 1994; F-101-6-1-0-4
  - Design competition, 1990 - 1998; F-101-6-2; 13 cm of textual records 1 moving image document 1 artifact
    Moving images; Textual records; Artefacts
    - Vancouver Public Art Committee - Correspondence and Resolutions, 1990 - 1997; F-101-6-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Subcommittee Minutes, 1992 - 1993; F-101-6-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Vancouver Park Board - Letters and Resolutions, 1993 - 1997; F-101-6-2-0-3
    - Correspondence, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Design Competition Guidelines- French and English, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Jury - French and English, 1994 - 1998; F-101-6-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
      Restricted in whole
    - Receptions, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Copyright Holder Information, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 101-6)
    - Stage Two Contracts, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
    - Stage Two Submissions, Beth Alber, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
      - Original maquette and artwork by Beth Alber, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-10-1 (Model OBJ-3243)
        Artefacts
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-101-item10.
    - Stage Two Submissions, Helen Goodland, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
    - Stage Two Submissions, Susan Point, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
    - Design submissions 1/3, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-13.1 (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-2234)
    - Design submissions 1/3, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-13.2
    - Design submissions 1/3, 1994; F-101-6-2-0-13.3
  - Dedication languages, 1995 - 1997; F-101-6-3; 5 cm of textual records 2 sound recordings
    Sound recordings; Textual records
    - Research, 1995 - 1997; F-101-6-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
    - Translations, 1995 - 1997; F-101-6-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
      - Dedication languages, 1997; F-101-6-3-0-2-1 (Audio cassette OBJ-3244, Audio cassette OBJ-3245)
        Sound recordings
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-101-6-3-6.1 (orig), F-101-item3, F-101-item4.
    - Questionnaires and Summaries, 1996; F-101-6-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
    - Decision Making, Processes and Summary, 1996 - 1997; F-101-6-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
    - Teleconference, 1997; F-101-6-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
      - Audiocassette and teleconference, 1997; F-101-6-3-0-5-1; 2 audio cassettes 2 .wav files (Audio cassette OBJ-3246, Audio cassette OBJ-3247)
        Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
        .wav files also available in .mp3 format.
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-101-6-3-5.1 (orig), F-101-item1, F-101-item2.
        - OBJ-3246_SideA.wav
        - OBJ-3246_SideB.wav
- Exhibits records, 1994 - 1997; F-101-7; 4 cm of textual records; The program for the exhibit at the Vancouver Art Gallery is in French and English.
  Series consists of records relating to the art gallery exhibitions of sixteen Special Mention designs which the Jury selected from the national design competition for the Monument, as well as the three finalists' stage two designs. Activities documented include the first exhibit, Giving Voice, at the Vancouver Art Gallery in 1994, and the touring exhibits at the Royal Ontario Museum in Toronto in 1995, the Nickel Arts Museum in Calgary in 1996 and the Surrey Art Gallery in 1997. Includes programs and other published materials. Also includes mock-up drawing of exhibit lay-out.
  - Three Finalists, 1994; F-101-7-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
  - 16 Special Mention Artists, [ca 1994] - [ca 1997]; F-101-7-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
  - Published Materials - French and English, 1994; F-101-7-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
  - Design Competition Showings, 1994 - 1997; F-101-7-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 101-7)
- Construction records, 1995 - 1998; F-101-8; 11 cm of textual records; Translations for the Dedication are provided in Chinese, Swahili, French, Chinook Jargon, Hindi, and Spanish. Oral readings of these dedications are included on audiotape in the Unveiling Ceremony series.
  Series consists of records related to the building of Marker of Change, the Women's Monument by the artist, Beth Alber. The Groundbreaking Ceremony is also documented.
  The monument consists of fourteen pink Laurentian granite "benches" arranged in a wide circle approximately ninety feet in diameter. Each bench approximates the length of a woman's body (5'5"), representing and inscribed with the name of one of the murdered women. (Each name appears on the side of the bench facing into the circle.) A horizontal vulva-shaped hollow, sand-blasted into the top surface of each bench, gathers rainwater, a symbolic vessel for tears and memory. Every other bench has an inscription of the Dedication in one of seven languages. The Dedication reads:
  The fourteen women named here were
  murdered December 6, 1989
  University of Montreal.
  We, their sisters and brothers,
  remember, and work for a better world.
  In memory and in grief for all women
  who have been murdered by men.
  For women of all countries, all classes,
  all ages, all colours.
  Surrounding the benches is a protective ring of clay tiles with over five thousand names of individuals and groups who donated to the Project. Tiles inscribed with epitaphs written by the families are located across from the bench of their respective daughters or sisters. A feather inscription designed by Susan Point is incised in Genevieve Bergeron's bench to signify to all First Nations people that the language inscribed there, Chinook, is First Nations. An orientation stand at one corner of the site has key text written in Braille and raised lettering for people who are visually impaired. The site is wheelchair accessible.